Today, we are going to do Puja for Navaratri.
Yesterday you saw a beautiful description of Navaratri, and how the Mother Goddess has
created all kinds of powers within you. It's not that only She has the powers,
but you all have the powers and you can all work it out. You can all find out whether these powers
are there or not. With us the Realization is very important, but there the Kundalini
has given you this Realization. Of course Kundalini is a part, or we can say reflection,
of Adi Shakti, and also
the Jagadamba is also part of Adi Shakti.
She is placed in the center of two Hearts, which is a very important point.
Now, all these powers are placed in that Chakra. So you imagine how many of these powers must be.
And Her powers are expressed through the center Heart in all the Ganas you have around your body.
Now these Ganas are the ones who do give you the protection, give you the sleep,
give you the energy, give you the blessings - all of them are at work all the time - and these
bodies are extremely dedicated and connected all the time to the Mother Amba: we can call, Jagadamba.
Now She is the Mother of the universe; so you can imagine it, how busy She has to be
to look after the whole universe. When this center becomes weak, that means Her connection
with the Ganas is reduced. Ganas also are weak, and all the powers that could be exercised,
cannot be done because of this weakness. It's a very subtle center because it is Mother's center;
is impossible to understand the love of Mother. It's absolutely impossible.
When the girls get married, and they become mothers, then they start understanding how much their
mother must have done for them to come up. In the same way when Sahaja Yogis become good Sahaja Yogis,
like Ganas, they realize how much the Ganas had to have patience,
had to have love and intelligence, to fight the negativity. So all the forces of the Jagadamba act towards
hitting the negativity of all kinds.
That is Her first and foremost nature - is to destroy all the negativity that is in this
world and is against Sahaj, against you. Her destruction takes place in so many ways.
First of all, we have to know that if you sin against the Goddess, then all kinds of physical start problems
- like psychosomatic diseases, all kinds: we can say cancer, AIDS, all of them.
But some of the diseases have got also the mixed up with the Ganapati. Now Ganapati is the
Lord of all the Ganas. So, the Mother has Ganapati, and She controls all these Ganas
through her son Ganapati. It is so connected. So the sin against the Mother when we do - means
when we become immoral. Immoral means when we start indulging into things which are not
permitted by dharma. By dharma whatever is permitted is the legal. Now you people understand
Sahaj dharma innately, from within. I didn't have to tell you. Now you know this is wrong,
is wrong, this is right, this is right. So any such things when you try to do,
because She is a Mother, She takes time to punish you. No doubt. But if you commit a sin against the Father,
like boastfulness, talking big, being cruel, harsh and all that - immediately
the punishment comes in. But from Her, She being the Ocean of compassion, the punishment
is more delayed, and a full chance is given to the person to improve himself and guide himself.
But when the punishment starts, then you get into diseases which are of a very serious nature.
So it comes from one thing, what we call as fear. When somebody frightens you or aggresses you,
or becomes like a maskit as they say; somebody who is oppressed by aggressive people
or is threatened, intimidated, then a person starts losing faith in the powers of Mother.
As a result, such a person ...
So this center Heart is to be looked after.
Out of fear, if somebody is thrown on to the left side, away from the Mother,
because She is the one who gives us confidence, who gives us courage and bravery.
But if you are frightened, or if you are under fear, also you can be thrown to the left side;
and you can get into all kind of diseases which are very serious, incurable as they call them.
Another thing is if you are driven by your senses into indulgences without any dharma,
then also this central path throws away, you can say, you to the left side,
because you are not worthy of being at the lotus Feet of  the Mother. Now, this center is the one which
when we are afraid, the sternum bone starts moving like a remote control and informs all
the Ganas that the attack is coming. But when you deliberately go to the left side,
and get into indulgences, then they are not bothered. They said: "All right, go ahead, do what you like;
you can behave the way you want to behave." All these different types of movements towards the left,
takes you away from your Mother.
I'll tell you a story about somebody in America. He is a very old Sahaja Yogi, Indian.
He came out of his shop, where he was working, and got into his car - there was one man sitting with a dagger.
And he hit him with the dagger on the center Heart. And this fellow started bleeding.
He said, " I don't know what happened to me, Mother. I got such strength,
I caught hold of him and I started fighting with him, and I took the dagger from him.
He had the handle and the dagger came into my hand. And the fellow ran away.
But still I was not worried about my bleeding. What I did - I called my colleague who was coming out of the car,
I ran after him and he took me in his car for half-an-hour searching that fellow."
They didn't go to the police.
And then they went to the police. The police was surprised - the whole shirt was full of blood.
He said, "Nobody would believe." Even the police was shocked. "For half an hour
you were searching this fellow. Why didn't you come to the police?" He said,
"It would have taken half-an-hour for you to come, so we thought, better do it ourselves." See the courage!
Then, of course, he was taken to the hospital, and he was all right.
Just they stitched him up. But he is all right. That is the sign of a person who can never get
any one of these horrible diseases, because there is no fear in his mind, of any kind.
And, he is an Indian, he said: "I have never even slapped my own children. I have never
fought with anyone. I am not a wrestler by any chance, nothing of the kind. But it happened."
He says, " I don't know how, from where I got this shakti; and how I did it, I just don't know."
There are many stories like this they can tell you about Sahaja Yogis, and about so
many saints, how they were never afraid of attacking someone when somebody attacks them,
or of protecting themselves from all kinds of horrible things with their courage.
This is something one cannot believe sometimes, but it is happening, every day, I get letters
from people how they have been courageous. If you believe in the Goddess, then know that
She is extremely powerful; She is very intelligent; and if She has to protect you, She will protect
you out and out, in such a way that you will not know how you have been protected.
But this faith has to be developed. Faith has to be developed by experience also,
how you have been protected always; how you have been helped always; how you came out of so many crises.
But despite that if you get upset, worried, if some clouds appear in the sky of your life,
then if you get upset, that means you are still weak. So first thing,
if you are really worshipping the Goddess, then you should have no worry at all of any kind,
and you should have no fear at all. Go ahead, fearlessly. Whatever you are doing, do it fearlessly.
But at the same time I have to tell you the other side, that one should
not go about like a zombie, it doesn't mean that; saying all kinds of nonsensical things of the right side.
But if you have to do something, do it with clear-cut ideas, and also without any fear.
So all Her powers, you start manifesting it. A man who is fearless has nothing to worry about
- his sleep, his well-being, nothing. He is fearless. Again I say, "fearless" doesn't
mean you go on hitting everybody, saying all kinds of things, no. It means that you are fearless:
anybody who attacks you, you can always protect yourself. I mean, this story I told you,
because this was not a protection which was from within, like Goddess protecting
them, but actually protected himself. So the power had started working through him.
You should allow your mind, your body to project these powers. Otherwise we say here pujas, everything,
all right; and the power is there; but your mind which tells you "No, no, no, this is not so."
There's so many stories, so many miracles people have described about this.
So, first of all, you should not have any fear about anything. If you have done nothing wrong,
if you are on the right path, you will be always protected. Now remember this
- you will be always protected. Remember this and believe in this, that: "I am always protected."
This is something very difficult, because perhaps our mind gives ideas: "Oh God,
what will happen now; what is going to happen?"... this thing, that thing.
So first and foremost thing, as I said, is to be fearless - to make the Goddess expres Herself.s
Supposing now, take it like this: now all Ganas are following you. Now if the
leader of an army is a frightened personality, what will others do? Thus, you become dependent
upon yourself. This faith also must be developed. I have seen people who are sick -
so they must come and see Me, because they do not depend upon themselves. They can cure themselves.
There is no need for them to come and see Me. There are many cases where people have
cured themselves, cured others, just with prayer. But the faith, when it is not matured,
then they think I, I should treat them. I should touch them, I should do this, I should do that.
Now I have stopped it. I used to do once upon a time. Reason is, now you depend
upon yourself. Not only that you can help yourself, but you are going to help others.
But if you do not have faith in yourself, that you can cure, you can look after yourself,
you can protect yourself; so the whole thing becomes like a ... all the time the Mother has to do the job.
Now you, first of all, you have to feed the little baby; all right? You can get him aid,
look after him, do everything. But when he grows up, then he doesn't want his mother to feed him.
In the same way, the Sahaja Yogis now, how many years I have been working.
You have to grow up dignified and you should mature, so that you can yourself do things properly.
This maturity is there because your Mother has blessed you. All Her powers She has given you - every.
But one power, of patience, is difficult. You have to be patient like your Mother.
You might think it's very difficult. But try to be. Must have patience, first of all,
with yourself. I have known many people who think they are spiritually nothing and
they have not achieved anything. This is absolutely a sort of a escapicism, that you want to escape
your personality. Just see. If you introspect, you will find out that you have developed
into a real spiritual giant now. Nobody can touch you; you can do everything;
you can look after yourself; you can support others. Whatever are the powers of all these that
they were singing yesterday, all these powers are manifesting in you. But still you leave
it to chance and, I should say, you leave it to others, not to yourself.
Now this is one point that no one, so far, has done this kind of a job - is to connect
all the disciples to the Divine power. Because it is the Divine power of love, you must know
how to love others. That's very important. But again, when it comes to love, they will
love their child, love their wife; I mean it is very common in Sahaja Yoga. They are
too attached to their children. Before this, they were known to be absolutely selfish,
had no attachment for children or wife or anything. But now it is like a glue.
Children are glued to them, wife is glued to them and the family - very important.
This is another temptation from which you have to get out.
I am not saying that you have to give up your family or your child.
But, again I say, the detachment. The detachment is your power.
Watch everything with detachment. Now don't think that, "Oh, I came only a few days back
in Sahaja Yoga"...no. Don't think, "Somebody is higher than me; I am no good" ... no.
You just introspect yourself and see for yourself how many powers you have already got.
And the more you'll know, the more you'll become humble. It's very surprising. You'll become humble.
No fear of any kind. You can have fear if you have some, say, lot of money with you.
If you are very well educated, you might have fear of jealousies. If you have other
wealth like ornaments and things, you will be afraid of big thieves coming around.
If you are a politician, you might be afraid that somebody might take away your seat when
you are away. But, when it comes really to Sahaja Yoga, it's the other way round. Who
can steal your Self-realization? Tell me! Who can steal your powers? Who can steal your
vibrations? Think of it. And who can steal your love? Because it is coming from the Spirit,
which is eternal, and the flow is all the time there. Only when you go away from your Spirit,
then only you feel all these things, which one feels in the darkness.
Then another power of Mother is that She gives you a state in which you are a sakshi,
you are a witness, watching everything. You have tremendous patience; tremendous patience.
Whatever's happened, all right, let it be. This will be all right, that will be all right, this and that.
So you get rid of a horrible thing called anger. And this gives you such
a peaceful witness state, that you start becoming younger and younger. I will tell you,
some Sahaja Yogis whom I gave Realization, say, last year, this time I met them -
I could not recognize. They have suddenly become ten years younger. It's very surprising.
And I was Myself, had to confess that I really, I can't recognize that are you the same people,
or are you the son of that fellow?
So then, what happens to you is that you become a peaceful personality. Why? Because your
Mother is there always. This faith: She is always there, She is always with us,
always protecting us: but now we are grown up, so She has given us all the powers. All the property
She has given us; so what, what is there to be afraid of? But this faith has to be not
just a blind faith, but an enlightened faith. Now the difference is, in blind faith you
have faith but no powers. In enlightened faith, you have faith and all the powers. When that happens to you,
you start growing very much fast - first in your dharma. And you are not afraid of your virtues.
You tell people, talk about Sahaja Yoga everywhere, and it works, it clicks. Once you don't have any fear,
the whole picture will be clear to you, because you become a visionary:
what we call in Sanskrit "drishtas". Like see how C. S. Lewis could see our procession.
How could William Blake predict our future? How could Gyaneshwara, wrote about "Pasayadan",
which is a description of all the Sahaja Yogis? But all the time he is saying, "Now you get
up and walk, and do this, you are that, now you've got it." He is trying to assure people all the time.
How could Rabindranath Tagore see our going to Ganapatipule? How could it happen?
It happens only when people are in enlightened faith. In enlightened faith your Mother gives
you another very great power, is of discretion; of discretion. Somebody came to me,
"Mother,You see, this gentleman is very good, this, that; and You know nobody has looked after
him, this that... He is very well educated, very moneyed person...this, that." I said:
"All right, show Me the photograph." I saw the photograph. I said: "No - yes,better keep him out.
Absolutely. Keep him out!" He was amazed. "How You say keep him out absolutely?"
I saw the photograph, and in the photograph only how could Mother say that? I could feel
the vibrations. Immediately I said: "Is wrong."
One gentleman came here and told Me that some Nigerians have written letter to him,
that "You put thirty-five thousand pounds in the bank", or something like that, "and we'll
put our money, quite a lot, in millions, and then you can have one third of that." He came
and told Me this story. I said, "Really? Keep out of it." So he said, "Why?" " It's a scam."
When he went back to America, they found it was a scam. He said, "Mother, how did you know?"
I said: "You can feel the vibrations - so hot! So it is a scam." You have got vibrations.
You can feel your vibrations. Now if you don't want to use this new awareness, what is the use of coming to Sahaja Yoga?
He was very upset when I told him, "Forget it." He thought: "Why Mother is saying so?"
I said: "Now what do you need money for? You need money? All right. We have. Don't take
these things." When I told him it's a scam, he got a shock. When he went back, he found
out it was a scam. So at the airport only, he was on My feet prostrated. I said, "What
happened?"
"Mother, You are the limit. What You said is there." I said: "But it was the
vibrations which told Me that he is a cheat. So, if he says so, that he is going to give
you so much money, is not correct because his vibrations were so very bad." In this way,
you can gradually experience. With the experience, try to put the experience in your
heart and have faith in that experience. What were you? What have you become now?
How many experiences of Sahaja Yoga you had? - of the Mother's attention on you.
Now if you have that enlightened faith, enlightened faith in you, you become powerful...
You are powerless, because your faith is like this.
But if you become really a evolved, matured realized soul, then all your powers will work.
There's a fisherman in India, who is - I mean, he is a graduate though he is a fisherman.
So one day, he was going on a boat to another island to do Sahaja Yoga. And when he came
out of his hut, he found huge big clouds, black ones, hovering and the Vishnumaya playing.
Just he stood on the shore and told Vishnumaya, "Please tell these clouds to behave themselves.
I am going for the work of Mother, and dare not trouble me on the way." Just told it.
The people who were with him, told me that this Harishchandra was talking like that.
They got into the boat. They did the program, came home. When he went into his boat, the rain started.
So you control all five elements by your enlightened faith. For which you don't even have to say
anything. The powers are so great that they act. See now: today when the Puja was to be done,
suddenly it became pleasant. I didn't ask. Just it became pleasant, much better
than yesterday: could have been very cold. But this should become again, a faith which
is reality. If you remember last time, we had a horrible rain and the whole thing was
jumping up and people had to pull all these pillars down. As soon as they started saying
My "Jai", it stopped. Now, this experience should make you; there was no need for you
to pull the ... these pillars, but you had to just sing My "Jai", that's all. Instead of that,
you were busy with pulling all of you that thing. I was just looking at you,
I didn't know what to say anything; I said, "Let them try."
So these ordeals also come to make you mature. These ordeals if they are not there,
These ordeals if they do not come, then you will not supersede them; and if you will not supersede them,
you will not know what is your faith. A person who is standing on the shore will say,
"I don't know how to swim." But supposing you made him jump into the water and he swims,
then he knows that he can swim. Because you do not know what you have become.
You do not know that you can swim. You do not know that you can also save others.
You are still busy with small, small, little, little things here and there. But if you just know what you have become,
then you are going to completely change. Your smallness, which looks like a little particle,
will cover the whole sky. But this power that is within you, will not give you ego.
One thing, the test is, it makes you humble. This is one of the things: that it makes you humble,
and extremely loving and compassionate. You will not hurt other people
with these powers; that's the sign: it is Mother's love, power of Mother's love.
A person who has a mother, very loving and nice, it's a psychological fact, becomes a very nice person;
it's a psychological fact.
So now if you realize what you are now, what you have become. Navaratri Puja is,
that's why, is a very, very powerful Puja in a way: because it manifests, opens out the channels
of your power, that's why it's very, very important; and since morning I have been just
flowing with vibrations, tremendous, it was like a waterfall of vibrations. And the whole
time I am seeing light, light, light, light; I was thinking, "Now I don't know what am
I going to speak or something." That's why I closed My eyes, because all the time there
will be something else I will be seeing and not you people; so better, I thought,
I'll close My eyes. But now you are the light. You are the light. Light is not afraid of
darkness, is it? Because, it can remove the darkness. That's what you are, but you don't
know what you are, and you live with very small, very small ideas about yourself.
I am not saying that you should become like gurus that go round talking big, with two
horns on their head, no. What is your decoration is your humility, is your kindness, is your sweetness,
and the way you handle people. You will be amazed, I also tell people when
I find there is something wrong with them. I also do it, no doubt; but in a way that
the person understands it is for the benevolence of that person. So the whole personality,
the whole temperament, everything changes; the whole face changes; the whole movement
changes. The style of talking changes, automatically as if you know the machinery has changed,
within. So you develop the qualities of a real Mahayogi.
This Mahayogi condition is achieved by many people also before, but they had to go through
very circuitous life. They had to give up everything, not to show, but really from the
heart they had to detach. They had to get out of it, go to some far-fetched places,
and live on ordinary food. All kinds of . . .even Buddha suffered so much. Christ suffered so much.
They were Incarnations but still they had to suffer. Rama suffered so much;
Shri Krishna suffered so much: imagine. Now you people didn't have to suffer. On the contrary
you all came out of the suffering: enjoyment, music, everything. But to enjoy Sahaja Yoga,
in Niranand - absolutely without anything else but joy - then one has to know that he
should give up all the myths with which he is living. All kinds of myths there are.
Some people have myths: "We are very poor". Some have myths: "We are very rich".
Some have this thing that "We are very unhappy". Some have that "We are very happy".
All kinds of myths these are. These are all myths. What is the thing is the complete emptiness; complete emptiness.
That is joy. This emptiness is filled with joy. Complete emptiness.
Then you don't expect anything from anyone. And this emptiness from within is actually, gives
chance to compassion and love to enter into you. Supposing there is something in a pot
already, what can you pour into it? What can you give into it? So if you are completely
empty within, there's nothing of this nonsense of the past and the future: the aspirations,
the ambitions, all those things, and falsehood. If you just become empty, it is filled in
with nothing but joy, and joy of such a eternal nature. You never asked for it; you do not
look forward to it. It is there, all the time. And this is what I wish today you people can feel it.
As you know, the Devi's things are so very deep and subtle: how She took the form of
a Mother and how She looked after Her bhaktas with love; how She fought demons and also negativity.
But now the demons have entered into your hearts; these false gurus have entered
into your brains. Through these horrible books so many things are coming, all the time attacking you.
Even if you kill those demons, still they'll be lingering in your heads. They should
be actually killed when they, once they are reflected into your mind, have gone away.
Then only it's possible to eliminate them. Otherwise, they will go away but leave their
bhoots into your heads. So these negativities, which come from wrong type of following you
have had, from wrong books you have been reading, also in Sahaja Yoga when you come, you can
be misled by some people - it's possible. In that case also, forgive that person. That person may improve,
but you may continue with the same ideas and funny things and will suddenly come up.
So the quality is of compassion and love, fearlessness and courage and the complete emptiness.
In this emptiness, then, you are not worried about what you have to achieve,
how many people you have to gather, how many must come to Sahaja Yoga - not bothered about that.
Automatically it will work out, but you would not desire for it, and you will not hanker:
"Oh my God," say, "There is not many people, what to do?"... this, that.
It is good for us in a way, because where is the place in heaven for so many stupid people?
So we should not run after people who are negative and useless. But we must definitely
take over the people who are genuinely good. One thing more I would like to tell you, that
automatically such people are dropped out in Sahaja Yoga. In one shot they will go away.
They don't stay, because they don't deserve to be there. They don't deserve to have the
Mother's powers. So this happens in a very beautiful, subtle manner. And I see,
I go late always to any program, so those who are useless just disappear. And some of them disappear half -way through,
because nothing goes into their head, really, they don't understand anything,
so they go away. So now the ones which are left are the real seekers of truth
and they get, all of them, Realization. In Sanskrit they call it "cheyen" - means "selection".
This is a natural selection that takes place, and how people go away and how they come back to Sahaja Yoga,
it's very interesting. This is a common happening in Sahaja Yoga, you know.
You should not get upset. Now if you get too many people, say from Russia,
and not so much from Switzerland, maybe you might think that way; but now it's not that bad.
Then we should not worry, because we are no more Russians or Swiss. We are superhuman beings,
we are Sahaja Yogis. Whether they are Russians or whether they are Indians or
from some African land, it's all right. As long as they are Sahaja Yogis, we should be
happy. If the Swiss are coming to Sahaja Yoga, we should be happy. So this attachment,
in a way, is good to begin with, that you want to bring more Swiss, because you want to have company.
Now you can't live with one person in a jungle, with all the others non-Sahaja Yogis,
you see - difficult. So you want to have company. So you want to have more and
more and more. But doesn't matter. As many as there are sufficient,
and we shouldn't worry about those things, the number.
But when we want to share our love, then we do feel the dearth. Not because we are Swiss,
but because we cannot share. That time a new personality rises, and this new personality
is the one which works. I mean we are not giving you any money; there are no awards for you.
There's no way there's much encouragement, like we have your sort of a picture hanging here,
nothing of the kind. Can you imagine in any organization anybody would work like this,
the way you work? Nobody would. They give you awards, they give you bonuses,
also they give you promotions; they do all kinds of things, you see, to keep you going.
But we don't do anything in Sahaja Yoga. So what makes you work so hard in Sahaja Yoga,
what makes you spread Sahaja Yoga? Only thing is that you want to share. You can't help it,
it's like a drunkard you see. If he has a bottle, he must have at least one person to
share with him, because he thinks that it would be sinful: "As it is I am doing sin,
why not share with somebody else?" So it would be half-half divided. But in Sahaja Yoga you share it;
you want to spread it. It is because you are collective; you have become collective,
that's why. You want more to come in, more to join, to enjoy. You become a very noble
person, you see? Like, of course drunkards do that, but supposing somebody has a lottery,
or some, he gets a very big business, he won't like to share. But you think that "Why not?
If I am so much enjoying, why not others? Why not people have the same bliss as I have?"
So because you become extremely noble, so noble, you work so hard, so very hard to achieve it.
I mean, no words can describe My joy when I see you people working it so spontaneously.
Yesterday I saw the film, the whole drama, and I was really very much amazed and touched
that this Marathi music has come to Cabella. Can you imagine any Italian thinking of it?
Even hundred years to come he would not think. But how it has come so spontaneously and is
working out? Because there is a sense of collectivity.
The "New Age" people talk of is here, no doubt. This is the New Age, and new consciousness
is also there. But what is the "new" now is the new collectivity, and that collectivity acts,
that you want to spread: it acts, like your hunger, it is another kind of hunger,
that you want to create more Sahaja Yogis, you want to have more brothers and sisters,
and you want to help them so that they could come to the Pujas and all that and become
good Sahaja Yogis. Now this kind of an ambition or a joy or whatever you may call it,
is the whole plan, shows that in your heart, the collectivity is prospering. And that's why
you cannot enjoy Sahaja Yoga alone, sitting in the Himalayas -no. You want to have other people.
This is now the sign of how the Mother's love has taken roots in your hearts and how you
are all going to spread Sahaja Yoga. Of course I'm told that somebody in Australia making money
- Australia has been always a problem - they are making money out of this;
so I just don't know what to say, because this is, I can't understand. How can they think
of making money or doing all kinds of things, and doing all kinds of asahaj things?
Some sort of a headache comes up, doesn't matter. Leave it to Me. I'll manage it, whatever it is;
but you just become great lights of your Mother. That's what I have to request you tonight.
You have all the power flowing in you, you have the light which is enlightened,
but you must expand. Expand it more and more and more, and you will be surprised what Tukarama
has said, that, "I am like a small little particle of dust, and also
I am the whole sky." This is what is your personality.
May God bless you all.