Where am I?
Where should I go?
Am I lost? I’m confused.
I can hear something… It’s as
if there are two forces within me,
like two
wolves.
Sometimes I feel determined,
I don’t give in,
I’m intelligent,
shrewd, capable, but then I become
angry and aggressive:
I keep arguing with everyone, without
having to real reason.
I look for trouble everywhere and
I find it easily.
At other times I’m gentle,
understanding, affectionate
and generous but
then everything scares me.
I become lazy,
sad, introverted and I can’t see
the beauty
in anything.
It’s difficult to live like this!
I need to be determined, brave and to
never give up.
But also to be intuitive,
alert
and to have eyes that
can see in the dark.
The world
is in turmoil.
Maybe because we are never satisfied?
Our mind’s are never content and
this creates friction,
conflict, division, tension,
racism,  intolerance,
fear  and violence… We continuously
desire things
that give us superficial satisfaction
and that only appease us temporarily;
our all society is founded
upon this principle.
We are slaves to a form of
continuous greed:
we want to possess everything.
We desperately desire something
but as soon as we have it,
it soon looses its importance and our attentions
rapidly moves to other objects,
other goals, but in the end we
never feel fully satisfied.
We talk about world peace,
so why do we still have wars?
How can humanity achieve peace,
if we can’t feel it within…
within our souls?
The solution needs to be
found inside of us!
In a complete transformation of the inner being. why?
Because it is not possible to establish peace
in the world if individuals are not
in harmony with themselves.
Today a solution exists, that
is available for everyone.
There is an energy that acts in the
deepest and most profound part of each of us,
it’s a female energy that resides
in the sacrum bone:
she’s known as Kundalini.
How can this energy help us?
By spontaneously awakening
itself within us,
She dissolves any inner difficulties
or tensions.
It’s not something you should just
believe in,
the Kundalini actually
activates a energetic system
that we can physically feel.
Inner peace
Inner peace? That's cool! Inner peace of what?
It is the next phase of your training.
Every master
must find his path
to inner peace. Some choose to meditate for fifty
years
in a cave just like this without the
slightest taste
of food or water.
Or? Sometimes it's through pain and
suffering as I did.
Po the day you were chosen as Dragon
warrior
was the worst day of my life. But once I
realized the problem
was not you but within me I found inner peace
and was able to harness the flow of the universe.
Inner peace may be achieved
thanks to the Kundalini
that awakens innate qualities
within the human being
such as respect for each other, tolerance,
solidarity and she permits us
to establish
a state of harmony and consistency that helps
us to move in the best direction.
On the 21st March 1923
a very special personality was born
Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi
promoter of a subtle and deep inner revolution.
A unique figure,
who undeniably deserves to be nominated
among the great personalities of
this century like
Gandhi, Martin Luther King
and Nelson Mandela.
Shri Mataji, in fact, not only spread
the message of peace,
or fought for social change.
She went beyond, directly to the
root of human problems:
She found the key to inner transformation
through the spontaneous awakening
of the Kundalini.
When the Kundalini rises,
She connects with the all-pervading energy
and it is through this union that we experience
inner peace.
Such a beautiful power
is all-pervading,
into every atom and
into every living primule
into every living being.
It acts so beautifully that we don’t even
feel the smoothness of it. We don’t even see
a flower flowering, blossoming opening, we don’t see that.
It just blossoms and we say, “Oh, today there is a flower.”
It just so sweetly, so beautifully,
that we do not even feel the existence of it
in any way – but it exists.
And unless and until we are connected with that power
we cannot know the ultimate reality
because the spirit within us is not in our attention.
It’s the Kundalini that helps us calm
our continuous mental activity,
all these excessive thoughts
that fill our minds and make
us react badly!
They constantly take us to the future
or to the past preventing us from
living the reality of the present.
Preventing us from being
in the moment.
So I believe that in everyone of us
we have inside of us
all the truth and the knowledge that we need to grow
and I think that with meditation that's the only way
I can actually get connected with this truth and this knowledge
So I meditate so I can grow and
so I can evolve.I think everybody needs to evolve. What's the point of stopping?
I meditate
because I want to feel the
inner joy. I felt it.
I want to fell it again and again
I meditate because it helps me be a more balanced person
and it helps me with my studies
And it's very very joyful when
you reach that state, where you're not thinking at all
and you can just witness everything
Why I meditate? I believe and I feel that
since I started meditating, everything has changed
everything around you changes, not just inwardly
but everything around you changes, the people...
It's the best thing that happened in my life.
Basically this energy rises, goes through all our chakras
comes out through our fontanel and connects everyone.
And that's the reason why we are able to feel this freedom, this peace.
It connects each individual, we are all connected through this energy
losing all thoughts that had come to your mind...
It's simply the nicest feeling that one can have
it makes me relax, feel very calm and achieve inner peace.
It give me peace. I feel more peaceful when I meditate and also it helps me to get into a state of...
stay in the center.
It gives me the capacity to understand
who I am and who I can become.
Sahaja Yoga can be anything you want,
because it hasn't actually any limitations.